Software Engineering Radio episode 116,
The Semantic Web with Jim Hendler.
This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days. Thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
support.
Hello listeners, welcome to new episode
of Software Engineering Radio.
In this episode we're talking to James
Hendler. He is
a professor at the Rensselaer
Polytechnic Institute and he is one of
the
inventors or of the leading figures in
the semantic web space. So we're
obviously going to talk about the
semantic web.
Um, please excuse the not so great audio
quality. We did the recording via Skype
and
as you all know sometimes it works
better, sometimes it doesn't.
Uh, James' microphone probably also
wasn't the best, but we did clean up the
audio quite some. It's easy to listen
to. When I edited it I had no problems.
But anyway, it's not up to the usual
standard.
Anyway, so here's the
episode.
Welcome Jim. Why don't you introduce
yourself to our listeners?
My name is Jim Hendler. Right now I'm a
uh, professor at Rensselaer Polytechnic
Institute or RPI
in the states, where I have just
recently moved in uh,
past year to create a center focusing on
the semantic web and
web related applications and research
into the web.
Uh, prior to this I was at the
University of Maryland for
the past couple of decades and in that
time, among other things, we created
some of the early technologies and what
are now called semantic web. So, I've
been doing this for a long time.
One of the ways I'm known better is that
I went to uh the US funding agency that
was the DARPA and helped create a
program called DAML, which helped fund
the uh early semantic web work and
publish some early articles with Tim
Berners-Lee on
the semantic web concept.
Yeah, so so you were you were described
to me as the father of the semantic web.
So, that explains it.
I would I would call Tim the father of
the semantic web. I I I was more the uh
I don't know what, maybe the midwife.
Okay. So, um I guess
all of our listeners know what the web
is. They probably won't know in detail
what the semantic web is. So, can you
can you give us a a definition or a
vision or a explanation of what it is?
Sure. We spend a lot of our time trying
to think of very fast ways to explain it
and the one that I like best is right
now if I have a document, I can put it
on the web and it can point to any other
document on the web with a simple link.
But, if I have a database or a
spreadsheet, I can't put that on the web
and have it point at other databases or
spreadsheets. So, in a sense, create
figuring out what's the infrastructure
by which data and definitional
information can come to the web rather
than just documents, is at the heart of
the semantic web.
Mhm. I I've heard it called the web for
machines or for for the web for for
software or or or programs.
Yeah, there's a lot of different ways to
view it. The key concept is right now
the information on the web is primarily
described for human use.
Yep.
But if I'm using data or something like
that, it's very hard to describe that
for human use because what I need to do
is correlate it, aggregate it, collate
it, query it.
All things that sort of happen back
behind the
uh you know, sort of somewhere in the
infrastructure. And then when I present
it to the human, it's going to look like
a table or a text or a
Yeah.
website. So it's really about building
the new infrastructure for the web to
make uh far more of the data
work together. And of course, that will
require more machine-to-machine
integration of things.
Yeah.
So, can you talk a little bit about the
ingredients that will be necessary or
that are in place or have to be put in
place to make this um this goal
realistic or or feasible?
I guess I'd say there's three things you
need. So one is since we're creating
data on the web, we need a data format
that can include links.
So my database and your database, if I
want to integrate them, I need some way
of knowing what can be merged, what
can't be merged, which things link to
which other things. So the language, the
Resource Description Framework or RDF
Yep.
is primarily the language that
gives you that. So we need a standard
for the kind of data description.
The next thing you need is a means for
describing terms in that data. So um
if I have a a database, I look at a
column called C27:19,
and I see that it's filled with the
number 15.
Mhm.
That doesn't help me much if I want to
merge it with another database.
Yep.
If I know that that represents the age
of a person, uh
then I can find the another database
which has either other properties of
that person or or ages of other people,
now I know how to put them together. So,
we call that an ontology or a domain
description in a formal
um
way to represent it.
Mhm.
Is that where the term semantic comes in
because these ontologies define the
meaning of things in a common or
standardized or agreed upon way or or
framework?
Yeah, that's basically it.
Okay.
The key is that um if I want to
represent if I want to link data
together, I really tend to have to know
what it's about, and often it's about
something that's not in the database.
So, my employee database is about
people.
But to link my employee database to
something else, I may have to know
people drive cars or people own houses.
And that's when things get complicated
because there's nothing in my data
schema called a car or a house. So, we
have to be able to represent those
semantics external to the data.
If you talk about linking data, then you
don't mean uh having explicit hyperlinks
or links like references, but rather
joining disparate data by matching some
of its properties and and matching
disparate data sets against each other
and thereby joining them.
Well, so again, you're now talking more
of the technology of how to use it
Right.
than
that. In fact, I started to go down
those technologies and then moved up to
a slightly higher level.
Yeah.
But when you really want to play with
this stuff, so first of all, you need a
way to get the data out of a database
into a place where it can be merged or
you need a means to query the data
dynamically for that.
Yeah. Yeah.
So, RDF lets you create the what are
called triple stores or a different
description of the data. That's more
like a graph than a table. The
intuition behind that is easy. If I take
two tables and want to join them,
um it's hard to figure out which if I
don't know which columns line up with
each other columns or if some of the
columns don't line up, then I don't
really have a method to create a new
thing that will be a table. If I take
two trees and merge them, I can't
guarantee I get a tree, but if I take
two graphs and merge them, I can
guarantee I still get a graph. So, sort
of a directed labeled graph
is a way to think of what RDF is about.
So, you take your data, you turn it into
that kind of graph structure, and now
you can access things through graph
algorithms,
things like that. You need a a standard
way to query this sort of stuff. The
language SPARQL, S P A R Q L, is sort of
the semantic web extension of SQL that
lets you put in those graph patterns.
Uh you need some way to describe the
terms that aren't in the database, like
I said before, something about cars or
about houses.
So, we use the language called OWL
to
represent the ontologies. So, that's
really the the keys to the semantic web.
You need RDF
uh to describe the data, you need OWL to
sort of link terms about the data. Think
of it as just a higher-level data
schema. You need SPARQL, which is the
language for querying the data, and then
there's various other
uh emerging standards to deal with other
other things you may want to do in that
space.
Okay. So, um
well, we talked about the ingredients.
You said there's the common language,
RDF, there is the ontologies, OWL, and
what's number three?
Well, I said SPARQL, the query language.
Again, if you have a data language
without a data query language, it's hard
to use. There's some other things in
there, too. I mean, there are inference
engines, uh
systems that given data
against one of these ontologies, you
might be able to make some inference.
So, if I know you are a radio host, I
know you are a person
Mhm.
um and not a web page. Well, that could
be important if somebody if I'm doing a
search.
Yep.
Um
that kind of thing. So, if someone says
search for Marcus Welter, information
about Marcus Welter, I'd like to find
something very different than if they
ask me to search about your web page.
Yep.
Right? They may or may not be the same
thing. Certainly, if they ask me to
search about your blog or about your
columns or things like that, I have to
know what's about you and what's about
the things you've written.
And how do these inference engines
relate to RDF and OWL? How do they do
they How do they use those data
descriptions and and and standards?
Well, there are there are various
different ways, but the key is that
since those are now in a standard
format, so if in OWL I want to say a
graduate student is a kind of student, I
use a particular relation. So,
I can make that explicit. Furthermore,
getting a little more technical, you do
have software developers out there who
will be able to follow this.
Yeah.
We don't describe the terms just using
words. So, I don't just say car, I
actually give it a URI that's against a
So, http://
some website and then some document that
describes this has this relationship
described in it.
Ah.
That means you can actually dereference
the term to see what that description
is. So, that's where the language OWL
comes in. You can actually see some of
the machine-readable relations, which
legitimizes the inferences. But, the
other thing that's important is you
don't get the kind of accidental
coreference you get in English. So, one
of the things Google does is says the
word fish can be a name, it can be an
animal, it can be something you're
doing. If I say http://www.cs.cmu.edu,
you know, something,
Sure.
/animals#fish,
fish,
Yeah.
it gets a lot clearer
that that two people using that same
thing are not likely to be talking about
different things.
Right, so it's not just a word, it's
actually an identity which is
represented by your word.
so essentially we try to give each
concept an identifier. You try to make
data instances of against those
identifiers, and then you create a web
of how those identifiers can link to
each other and describe each other.
Mhm. If you talk about inference
engines, to me this sounds quite a bit
like Prolog. So, is there a a
relationship to this kind of logic
expressions that people might know from
Prolog?
You know, the the easiest answer is yes,
and the second easiest answer is no. So,
what I mean by that is in a sense,
bringing this stuff to the web is sort
of like bringing hypertext to the web. A
lot of the same tools apply,
but
things that work in the small don't work
in the large of the web. Things that
work in controlled closed systems don't
necessarily work in large-scale open
systems.
Yep.
So, much as the early hypertext tools
are relevant to what eventually happened
on the web, but not usually
what works on the web. Same thing. So, I
may use Prolog to power a tool that's
doing something with semantic web data,
but I could also be using, you know, any
other language, Java, Ruby on Rails,
scripting languages, you know, explicit
languages, or I can go get um
there's, you know, tools out there. So,
something like Pellet is a reasoner, a
particular inference engine
tied to the language OWL. So, if I don't
want to build my own, I can I can just
call that one remotely or, you know, use
it as a tool.
Yeah, so the reason why I asked was
because of this um inferencing, which is
also a a property or a characteristic of
of how Prolog works.
Yeah, so so essentially you start from
agreement. We just know two terms mean
the same thing.
Yep.
Then we can say, given something is
using that term and is related by a
certain relation to another term, maybe
I know something about it. So, if I say
um
that student is a relationship Well,
like um
student at relates a person to a
university.
Mhm. I think
And I would know that if I saw
uh you know, John Smith student at RPI,
even if I knew nothing else, I know that
John Smith must be that kind of person
and RPI must be a university.
Yep.
But again, against these technical
definitions in these documents that are
dereferenceable.
So, I I think Prolog uses something
called first-order predicate logic,
right? Is Is that also used in OWL?
Part Part of the problem is there are
different people who have different
ideas about how you should do inference
in this space.
I actually a talk I've been giving
recently, and I will be giving at the
Linked Data Conference in a couple
weeks, is all about there's very
different views about what we're trying
to do, and several of these different
views now have return on investment
happening. I can talk about that if you
want, but
Mhm.
the key difference is some of them you
really want the reasoning to be very,
very precise and very carefully
controlled, and there's one view of OWL
that says this called description logic
reasoning. So, one view of OWL says,
"Limit your OWL to things where the
description logics will return sound and
complete
answers." There's another view which
says, "You know, I'm doing
recommendations of friends in a
large-scale social network, and if I had
a little bit of inference, then I could
do a better job
than Facebook does now. That would make
me some money. So, I don't really care
about these complex, sound, and complete
thing. I just need some very simple
inferences."
Mhm.
So, in a sense, Prolog you can build it
with restrictions or build it
unrestricted. This This stuff has some
of that same flavor.
Okay.
When I was preparing this uh this
episode and and also browsed a little
bit around your website, I I saw that
you've been working in AI uh a while
ago.
So, is there a relationship um from the
AI
world or topic or or or stuff to the to
the semantic web beyond the logic stuff?
You know, again, I would go back to that
hypertext analogy.
Yeah.
The the semantic web technology derives
from several technologies.
The The name sort of gives us the hint.
One is semantic, which derives sort of
connotes the AI side, but the other one
is web.
Yep.
So, essentially, the real challenge in
the semantic web has been taking AI,
which was built for closed and carefully
controlled systems, and bringing it into
this much wider world of the web, where
you have open, dynamic change. So, you
know, AI never had to deal with with
going to look up whether something was a
legal reference and getting a 404.
Mhm.
Right? On the web, you have to deal with
that. So, AI systems, for example, have
traditionally assumed that all of the
facts you know are consistent are are
correct with respect to each other. But,
you know, on the web, we get
disagreements, we get error, we get
fraud. So, a reasoner that said, "If I
can find two websites that disagree with
each other, I can prove you owe me
money."
Right? Would be a wonderful thing to
have on the web, but only if other
people would believe it, which they
wouldn't.
Yeah.
So, from a research perspective, some of
what we've been having to do is
re-examine AI as an open, dynamic,
web-scale system. And that's where a lot
of the exciting research for those of us
who are at universities comes in.
Mhm. You already mentioned that um
the semantic web uses obviously web
technology, and I guess that's basically
HTTP and XML, right?
Well, I mean, we're built on top of
HTTP,
uh X X H T X HTML. This RDF layer sits
on top of that. Uh U R I's for naming,
things like that. So, yes, very much on
top of those web um
things. In fact, one of the big changes
that's happened over the past couple
years, the term web 3.0
has been coined recently to talk about
sort of the applied early
Well, the semantic web startups in the
web space primarily.
And what you're really seeing there is
web application developers have
discovered the use of these R D F
systems to do things that are very hard
to do in relational data systems.
So, again, it's still very much just web
technology with H T T P, but now you're
doing H T T P with a sparkle query. So,
so right now on a web to do a web
application, very often what you do is
you go to a web page,
it queries to a back end that gets data,
turns it into a web presentation of that
data, and then you scrape that data to
get it into your database. You can query
that data directly,
you'd have a significantly easier time.
The problem is you can't query that data
directly unless you have all those
things we've been discussing, common
terms, common formats, ways to interact
So, sparkle plus R D F plus owl is
really the tool set that lets you start
doing that stuff. And
uh companies like Radar Networks in the
States or Metaweb or Garlic in the UK,
uh Onto, anything that starts with O N T
O and then has other letters after them,
they're
um
or Australia, you'll find. I mean, a lot
of this growth of new companies has come
less from the A I side getting the
benefit from the web and much more from
the web side
really discovering that a tiny bit of of
this A I stuff is very useful.
I think there is an an interesting thing
here and that you said that um the
Semantic Web is also sometimes called
Web 3.0.
I had sometimes the impression that
really the Semantic Web should have been
Web 2.0, but then there came the other
Web 2.0 and
I mean what I want to say with that is
that the Semantic Web technologies are
relatively old, but haven't like really
taken off for a while. Is is that fair
judgment?
You know, I think I think that's fair to
some degree. I mean certainly we you
know, Microsoft has been working working
on it since 95, 96.
It really got a lot more visibility
around 2001, 2002. So most people date
Semantic Web to an article in Scientific
American that Tim Berners-Lee and I
wrote that came out in 2001, although it
was around before that.
Um,
but
but it's just like any technology. First
the standards have to get developed and
mature, then they have to get accepted.
So there've been a lot of chickens and
eggs.
Yeah.
And I think what's happened is you've
really seen over the past year and a
half
a big change in that space. Enough is
out there now that you can really create
an application from scratch very
quickly,
start building the pieces, get it into a
web framework. They're starting to be
for example
server farm implementations, a lot of
things that were single machine
even 6 months ago. So it's
much larger scaling and things like that
has become possible.
Would you count things like tagging, you
know, this wisdom of the crowd stuff?
Would you count that as being part of
the Semantic Web or is that like more or
less the opposite where you have the
semantics in the people and you you
exploit the huge amounts of people to
tag things semantically in quotes?
You ask questions where I could go on
for hours, but won't. But it's the fact
that it's hard not to. But let me let me
put it this way. Think about the the If
you go to Flickr
and you take my first name, James,
Mhm.
you will find 900,000 images have been
tagged with that name.
Yeah.
Now, it doesn't seem to make sense to me
that a lot of people go out there and
use James as a search term
Yeah.
at Flickr itself.
What instead happens is you go into some
context. So, if you went to my wife's
area on Flickr,
Mhm.
then you would know James is likely to
be me, or if we had a child, or if we
had a cousin, or if you go to a movie
thing, James may be James Bond or James
Dean.
Yeah.
So, again, once you get into a context,
those social tags are very, very
powerful.
Mhm.
And in fact, that's what a lot of the
Web 2.0 sites have been focusing on more
recently. You actually see less tagging
than you used to, and much more focus on
the social interaction.
Right. Yeah.
Uh the semantic web, the terms we're
using are predefined.
In essence, if you can figure out how to
get people's terms over to that
terminology,
then you get some real advantages, cuz
you know this James is being used
particularly for a person, and it's this
person, and they're a professor, and
they have these things. So, the trick
is, they're really two very different
technologies. I think in the early days
of semantic web, we undervalued the
importance of the social context.
Mhm.
I think a lot of the early uh some of
the early Web 2.0 people, microformats
and things like that, referred to
themselves as the small less semantic
web.
They got the social part right.
Yeah.
We're missing some of the fact that the
vocabulary
is important. In fact, there's an
emerging set of some new standards and
some new tools, which are bringing those
things together. If you look at Yahoo's
recently announced SearchMonkey,
Mhm.
uh so, they want to open up the search
engine, make much more things available
to the user, the application developer,
etc. They are making some of these
technologies available as a way to
do that.
So, you can now take your tagging type
approaches,
tie things into these more technical
vocabularies, and then use the technical
vocabularies for querying, for
searching, etc.
Okay. We we talked about the
technologies um that are in place. They
are RDF, OWL, SPARQL, and GRDDL. I don't
know, GRDDL or what do you How do you
pronounce that?
Yeah, I didn't I didn't talk I didn't
talk too much about GRDDL, but GRDDL is
one of these things for and there's
another one called RDFa are aimed at
making it so you can take XHTML
web pages, embed this thing in it so
that if you do an HTTP request in a
human-readable format, so you do HTTP
content type XML, you'll get one you'll
get the human-readable
form. If you do content type RDF, you'll
get the machine-readable form.
Mhm. So, right. My my my question would
have been or or is or what kind of tool
support is there for these technologies?
What kind of tools do you need? And and
what's the status of those tools today?
I think that's where there's been the
biggest change over, you know, again,
first you have to get people interested
in technology. The tools have to
transition out of research labs. What
we're really seeing now is a very wide
range. There are open-source tools
for So,
if you kind of think of the ecosystem of
building one of these, you need some way
to describe your data, some way to query
your data, a way to build these
um the domain descriptions, ontologies,
a way to put things into websites, a
thing to search or crawl, etc. etc. All
of those things are now available.
Um
For a while, there was a small number of
them. So, for example, HP had a tool
called Jena,
which was for We we use it the the term
triple store is often used for the for
an RDF database.
Mhm. So, Jena was sort of the only open
source triple store out there. Now,
there were there were
uh at least dozens out there written in
just about every language. So, you know,
if you're a Ruby developer, if you're a
Java developer, if you're a C developer,
you you have you know, you can get the
tools in the languages you want.
Yeah.
Uh there's starting to be lots more of
these tools sold. There are companies
that have built very, very large-scale
um proprietary infrastructure. So, the
Garlic company has its own store.
There's other companies that have built
similar type things and are making it
available as a service. So, instead of
you hosting your own billion triples,
Yep.
you get someone who will host them for
you and then you interact with them
through a web interface.
Things like that. So, we're really at
the point now where finding the tools is
not the hard part and putting them
together is relatively straightforward.
It's really understanding the technology
that's still growing thing. And again,
it's you know, again, as any new
technology comes out, people have to
learn to use it.
Yep. Is Is there like integration with
mainstream stuff? Like, for example,
some kind of I don't know, RDF store
based on top of Oracle or something so
that can it can be integrated with my
legacy data and infrastructure?
So, uh sort of is the answer. So, Oracle
has actually has an RDF store is adding
OWL now.
Mhm.
Um in in their uh
10 and 11G product. But, um
you know, the integration with your
legacy data still requires some work. It
doesn't sort of
Right.
automatically get exported as RDF just
because you're using the tools. You
still have to build the equivalent of a
schema or an ontology. So, there's still
work to be done, but but again, it's
much easier. Getting the stuff to the
web. So, when I started this, you know,
you had a lot of this raw triple stuff.
Yep.
And you want to look at it on the web,
it didn't look very pretty. Now, people
have developed a lot of standard
visualizations, things like that, so you
invoke a web There's uh a conference
called the Semantic Technology
Conference, which is held yearly. Each
year we've been getting about 30% more
people than the year before. This year
we had about 1,000
Mhm.
Whereas you heard people talking about
scalable triple stores. So, again, if if
anything, the problem now is that
there's a lot out there and it's hard to
find as opposed to that there's nothing
out there.
All right.
Yeah. Well, you're already in the
exciting field, so you don't have to get
in there.
Okay, so thank you very much, Jim, for
being on the show.
Okay, thank you.
Thanks for downloading and listening to
Software Engineering Radio. Software
Engineering Radio is an educational
program brought to you by Hillside
Europe. If you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
If you want to support us, you can
donate to the SE Radio team via the
website, or you can advertise for SE
Radio, for example, by clicking on the
Digg, Reddit, Delicious, and Slashdot
buttons.
To contact the team, please send email
to team@se-radio.net,
or if it is specific to an episode,
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your comments.
This episode of SE Radio, as well as all
other episodes, are licensed under
Creative Commons 2.5 license. Please see
the website for details. Thanks to
Charlie Crow and the Podsafe Music
Network for the music used in this show.
The song is called Vegas Hard Rock
Shuffle.